Okay, today's דף *Daf* is ל"ו *Lamed Vav*. We'll start with ירושלמי
Yerushalmi. *Yerushalmi* פרק ד' *Perek Dalet* הלכה Halacha, ז' *Halacha Zayin*. The
משנה Mishnah? *Mishnah* is דיני ממונות dinei mamonot. טהרות וטומאות *Dinei Mamonos,
Taharos ve-Tumaos*. We've seen this already in the בבלי Bavli. *Bavli*. מתחילין
מן הגדול למשנה *Matchilin min ha-Gadol le-mishna* ובדיני נפשות מתחילין מן הצד
*u-ve-dinei nefashos matchilin min ha-tzad*. So monetary issues you start from the
elder of the court. The capital crimes you start from the side,
from the more junior members. הכל כשר לדון דיני ממונות dinei mamonot.
ואין הכל כשר לדון דיני נפשות dinei nefashot *Hakol kasher ladun dinei
mamonos ve-ein hakol kasher ladun dinei nefashos* אלא כוהנים לויים וישראלים המשיאים
לכהונה *ella Kohanim, Leviyim ve-Yisraelim hamesiyim le-Kehunah*, except for כוהנים *Kohanim*, לויים
*Leviyim*, and ישראלים *Yisraelim* whose daughters could marry כוהנים *Kohanim* as opposed
to, for example, like a חלל chalal *chalal* or something of that
nature. So it's an issue of lineage. Let's see the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. רבי Rabbi, אומר *Rabbi omer*: לא תענה על ריב *Lo saaneh
al riv*, רב כתיב Ktiv. *rav ketiv*. It's ריב *riv* without the
יוד *yud*. Don't respond back to what a רב *rav* has said,
שלא תענה אחרי הרב אלא קודם לרב *she-lo saaneh acharei ha-rav ella
kodem la-rav*. So therefore it's interesting, it's rather than sort of saying
once the elder has spoken you cannot respond and therefore you have
to speak first, which is what we say by דיני נפשות dinei
nefashot. *dinei nefashos*, this is saying you don't speak after the person
has spoken, so I'm jumping ahead to the next one.
So don't speak after the elder has spoken, so therefore you therefore
you must you have to be the one to speak first and
that's what we do by capital crimes. רבי Rabbi יוסי בן חנינא
אומר *Rabbi Yosei ben Chanina omer*: לא תענה על ריב *Lo saaneh
al riv*, רב כתיב *rav ketiv*, the same point, it's don't speak
after an elder, but he reads it differently, שלא תענה קודם לרב
*she-lo saaneh kodem la-rav*. Don't speak up, don't respond to an elder,
don't speak up in front of the elder, before the elder. The
elder has the right to speak first. You shouldn't jump up and
speak first, אלא לאחר הרב *ella le-achar ha-rav*, afterward. And so how
do you reconcile those two reads? So it seems that by monetary
cases you speak first and by capital crimes the רב *rav* speaks
first.
So did I get that wrong? Excuse me, reverse that, excuse me.
By monetary cases the רב *rav* speaks first, you give him the
right to speak first and that's the honor that you give him
and then presumably, and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* makes this point, it doesn't
mean that the conversation ends, somehow because the way the honor is
afforded in monetary issues is that the greater one speaks first, that
then allows the other ones to speak up afterward, even though they
might be a little bit hesitant and biased or whatever to
disagree and so on, but at least they're allowed to speak up
afterward after the elder has spoken up. But in capital crimes, because
you want to make sure that everybody sort of has their voice
heard, you afford the honor by not responding after the elder one
speaks, and therefore the way you do it is that the more
junior members are the ones who speak first. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: so it's a mirror images. Monetary
issues,
the senior one speaks first and the other ones presumably can respond,
and that's how honor is afforded. And capital crimes, nobody responds to,
disagrees with the elder one, so therefore the younger ones speak first.
Okay, רב אבא אמר *Rav Abba amar*: לא תענה אפילו אחר מאה
*Lo saaneh afilu achar me'ah*, דברי רבי Rabbi's פנחס Pinchas? *Divrei Rabbi
Pinchas*. Even after a hundred. What does this mean? So the רדב"ז
*Radvaz* says the best explanation. He says let's say this rule has
been violated. Let's say we're in דיני ממונות dinei mamonot *dinei mamonos*
and we're supposed to let the elder one speak first and a
hundred people have jumped in and spoken before the elder one. That
doesn't mean that I have no problem speaking after the elder. I
should just go ahead and go along, and you know I could
say look first of all everybody else is speaking, number two I'm
not
speaking before the elder one, I'm actually
speaking after this guy, it's not even in relation to the elder
one, the elder one clearly is being silent. No, even if everybody
has jumped in and already spoken, you're not allowed to speak first,
you know you have to afford the honor you have to afford
and make sure that now the elder one speaks, he should have
spoken first. Or you could say the opposite. Let's say it's a
capital crime and the elder one spoke first and everybody said something
back and they weren't supposed to,
or whatever the elder one spoke, the elder one spoke and everyone's
supposed to be quiet now, but no everyone kept on talking. Don't
say oh I can talk because now I'm not even directly responding
to the elder one, I'm just saying something about after what the
next guy said. No, everybody who jumps in is just adding to
the problem. I mean it's a very important message that it's not
enough that you don't just say hey you know I'm not creating
the problem, everybody else already did it. Everybody who now continues to
contribute, whether it's because you're speaking first and you should let the
elder one speak first, or whether it's because you're responding after the
elder one spoke and you're not supposed to respond, doesn't matter how
many people have done that already, you can't do it as well.
Okay, רב חילקיה בשם רבי Rabbi, סימון *Rav Chilkiah beshem Rabbi Simon*
אתפלגון רבי Rabbi יוחנן וריש לקיש *itpalgun Rabbi Yochanan ve-Resh Lakish*, a
debate of רבי Rabbi יוחנן וריש לקיש *Rabbi Yochanan ve-Resh Lakish*. חד
אמר
*chad amar*: דינינו כדיניהם dineinu k'dineihem *dineinu kedineihem*, our rules about who
gets to speak is similar to the rules. of the non-Jews.
וחד אמר אין דינינו כדיניהם. ein dineinu k'dineihem. No, it's not. מאן
דאמר Man d'amar דינינו כדיניהם ניחא, nicha, so if it's like their
rules that's fine. But מאן דאמר man d'amar אין דינינו כדיניהם, ein
dineinu k'dineihem, if you say it's not like their rules I show
you a verse that sounds like these are exactly the rules that
others follow. That the idea that in a capital crime a younger
member of the court speaks first. Where's there evidence that this is
what the non-Jews did? מה מקיים? Ma m'kayem? ויאמר יהודה. Vayomer Yehuda.
Yehuda said amongst his brothers about how to deal with Yosef. That
was a capital case. They were deciding what to do with Yosef's
life. Why did Yehuda speak first? He was a younger one. So
you see, and that's before מתן תורה. Matan Torah. It's non-Jews, but
whatever. It's not a תורה Torah law that there's also this idea
that younger ones speak first in a capital crime. ויאמר ממוכן. Vayomer
Memuchan. The seven people who were the advisors of אחשורוש. Achashveirosh. He
was listed last and he spoke first. And that was a question
of what to do with ושתי, Vashti, a possible capital case. Although
in the end they don't kill her, they just say she can't
come into the palace. Everybody thinks they killed her. Anyway, so look
you see that even without הלכה, Halacha? this is a normal type
of a practice that younger ones speak first in a junior case,
in a capital case. So the גמרא Gemara says, so what's the
answer if you say that it's unique to הלכה? So the answer
is they didn't speak first. It means ראו דברי יהודה, ra'u divrei
Yehuda, ראו דברי ממוכן. ra'u divrei Memuchan. It only records what יהודה
Yehuda said and what ממוכן Memuchan said, not because they spoke first,
but because they were the ones that people listened to. Okay. So
it's not telling you what everybody else said, which is reasonable. Okay.
ומנין שמתחילין בדיני נפשות מן הצד? U'minayin she'maschilin b'dinei nefashot min hatzad?
How do you know that you start from a junior member, although
we quoted a verse before we're going to quote another verse? So
תני שמואל הזקן קומי רבי אחא. Tani Shmuel Hazaken kumi Rabi Acha.
ויאמר דוד לאנשיו. Vayomer David l'anashav. It's another, this verse is also
quoted in the בבלי. Bavli חגרו איש
חרבו. Chigru ish charvo. This is when they were judging
נבל, Naval, and they said
everybody gird his loins. So it was a דיני נפשות dinei nefashot
type of a case.
And what were we?
So it says right. So חגרו איש חרבו. Chigru ish charvo.
I'm sorry, I misspoke. חגרו איש חרבו. Chigru ish charvo. ואחר כך
ישבו בדין על נבל. v'achar kach yeshvu badin al Naval. Excuse me
I said נבט, Navat, I meant נבל. Naval. So first of all
everybody did it and the end of the verse says that דוד
David did it as well and then they went to the judgment.
So that's the sword, an image of war was a type of
a debate in the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. Anyway, they're reading that
as the deliberations of the court and everybody spoke before דוד. David.
רב תימא בר פפיס בשם רב הושעיה. Rav Teima bar Pappayas b'shem
Rav Hoshaiah. אף בפסול משפחה מתחילין מן
הצד. Af b'psul mishpacha maschilin min hatzad. Even when you're dealing not
in a case of somebody's life but about somebody's personal status. Is
he a ממזר, mamzer, is he whatever? Even that's a case where
it's essentially a type of an issue of somebody's life and there
also you would start off from the side, you would not start
from the elder. Okay. הכל כשירים לדון דיני ממונות. Hakol k'sheirim ladun
dinei mamonot. רבי יהודה אומר אף. Rabi Yehuda omer af. Now we're
getting to the second part. Everybody can do דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot.
Who does the everybody include? אפילו ממזרים. Afilu mamzerim. Even ממזרים. mamzerim.
רבי יהודה אומר אין מדקדקין
ביין נסך. Rabi Yehuda omer ein m'dakdikin b'yayin nesech. Now what does
that have to do with anything? It's not clear. It could be
two types of statements of רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda that have been
just pasted together. One is ממזרים mamzerim can deal with דיני ממונות.
dinei mamonot The other is when it comes to יין נסך, yayin
nesech, you're not hyper-careful
about questions about, meaning and the way it's explained by the ראשונים
Rishonim it doesn't mean you're not careful, but it means that you're
not overly strict. That if a non-Jew maybe touches it in a
way that's completely out of context of how a normal touching would
be, maybe it should not become an issue of סתם יינם stam
yeinam and that's the way the ראשונים Rishonim quote it.
It's also interesting to wonder because wine is used as a metaphor
we're going to see soon for the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So is this
also saying that somehow in some types of a בית דין Beit
Din we're not
superly restrictive of who can sit on the בית דין. Beit Din.
כתיב. One verse says לא תטה משפט אביונך בריבו. Lo tateh mishpat
evyoncha b'rivo. אי אתה מטהו. Ei ata matehu.
So you can't tip, which here is read as judge against somebody
as a guilty verdict by one if it's a capital crime. That
you can't do for אביונך, evyoncha, your poor person, like a human.
אבל אתה מטה בדינו של שור. Aval ata mateh b'dino shel shor.
But a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, even though it requires twenty-three, we're
going to see exactly this in the בבלי Bavli. as well. That's
the one thing that's like דיני נפשות. dinei nefashos But other than
that, you can go ahead and everything else follows דיני ממונות dinei
mamonos because we're not trying to protect the life of the ox.
Actually we want to get rid of a possibly hazardous animal from
our midst. רבי אבהו בשם רבי יוחנן. Rabi Abbahu b'shem Rabi Yochanan.
ומלבד דברים שבין דיני ממונות לדיני נפשות. U'milvad devarim she'bein dinei mamonot
l'dinei nefashot. It means like all these things that are, so exactly
the word ומלבד u'milvad is a little funny, but it means that
this is the one thing about the need of twenty-three. That's the
one thing that you have by a שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. Everything
else in the list of the differences between monetary and capital crimes
would not apply. You don't have all those biases to ensure innocence
by a שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. All the rules you would follow
would be by דיני ממונות. dinei mamonos Who would speak first and
a majority of one and all those types of things. Now, כמה
אינון? Kama inun? And how much are these differences between דיני ממונות
dinei mamonos and דיני נפשות dinei nefashos listed in the משנה? Mishnah
אנן תנינן תשעה. Anan taninan tish'a. Our משנה Mishnah lists nine. We're
going to see it's also a question of numbers in the בבלי.
Bavli תני רבי חייא אחד עשר. Tani Rabi Chiya achad asar. רבי
חייא Rabi Chiya had eleven. רבי חייא. Rabi Chiya. האי דינא. Hai
dina. the ones in our משנה Mishna, nine, תרתי אחרייתא tartai achraiyasa
and two more. What are the two more? הסריס וכל מי שלא
ראה לו בנים כשר לדון דיני ממונות ולא דיני נפשות, Hasaris vechol
mi shelo raah lo banim kashar ladun dinei mamonos velo dinei nefashos,
that somebody who is a eunuch and has not had children can
do monetary cases and not capital crimes as רש"י Rashi and others
רמב"ם Rambam explain, that if a person hasn't gone through raising kids
they maybe don't have the right type of, you know, patience or
compassion and so on. ואמר רבי אבהו בשם רבי יוחנן Veamar Rabbi
Abbahu beshem Rabbi Yochanan אף פחות
מכן עשרים—and af pachos mikan esrim that's one. What's the other difference?
אף פחות מכן עשרים ומי שלא הביא שתי שערות כשר בדיני ממונות
ופסול בדיני נפשות. Af pachos mikan esrim umi shelo hevi shtei searos
kashar bedinei mamonos upasul bedinei nefashos. Somebody under twenty and it's and
somebody who doesn't have two pubic hairs, which is wild, sounds like
even a minor can deal with monetary cases, but certainly under twenty,
but not with capital crimes. You need a little greater like a
maturity.
Okay. והשאר בדינו של שור. Vehashear bedino shel shor. I'm sorry, yes,
and similarly as we said, all of the restrictions of דיני נפשות
do not apply to the ox. The only ox difference is the
twenty-three. רבי יוסי בן חנינא אומר תלת עשרה, Rabbi Yosi ben Chanina
omer telas esre, thirteen differences. והיי דינן, Vehai dinan,
the ones that we mentioned is eleven, תרתין אחרנייתא tartin achranyasa and
two more. דנים שני דיני ממונות ביום אחד ואין דנים דיני נפשות
ביום אחד, Danim shenei dinei mamonos beyom echad veein danim dinei nefashos
beyom echad, and that you can judge you can judge two monetary
cases in the same day but not two capital crimes in the
same
day. ואמר רבי אבין ואפילו נואף ונואפת, Veamar Rabbi Avin vaafilu noaf
venoafes, even an adulterer and an adulteress you can not judge them
in the same day. That sounds like it's even if it's ממש
mamash the same case and the same judgment, although as the בבלי
Bavli. elsewhere says, it's only if they're different judgments, one would get
סקילה sekilah and the other שריפה sreifah based on certain cases, but
maybe there are some times when you can judge them at the
same... Okay.
So that is though, I'm sorry, so how do we get the
thirteen? Oh, it seems like we're saying the eleven was the case
of סריס saris and not having had
kids, that's counted as two, general not having had kids. And the
other two is this issue of twenty and this issue about two
judgments in the same day. Okay, so that's the גמרא Gemara for
the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Now let's turn to the בבלי. Bavli We pick
up in the בבלי here on דף ל"ו daf lamed vav at
the שתי דוטס shtei dots about ten lines down, just totally paralleling
the ירושלמי. דיני ממונות הטיה על פי אחד. Dinei mamonos hatayah al
pi echad. אמר רב אנא הוינא במניינא דבי
רבי, Amar Rav ana havina beminyana devei Rabbi, I was in the
counting on a בית דין beis din of רבי, you know everybody's
being counted and took a vote. This actually is in a particular
context about a certain ruling about in גיטין Gittin about a סיקריקון.
sikrikon. Anyway, ומינאי דידי הוו מתחלי
ברישא, Uminai didi havu maschali bereisha, and they started with me first
even though it was seen as something which presumably would have been
a דיני ממונות dinei mamonos. case. It was a דיני ממונות dinei
mamonos case about a question about ownership of land, so they should
have started with רבי because you start with the elder by a
דיני ממונות dinei mamonos. case, but they started with me. והנן מתחילין
מן
הגדול
תנן, Vehanan maschilin min hagadol tanan, but don't we say in monetary
cases you start with the elder? אמר רב פפא בריה דרב אויא
ואי תימא רב הילל בריה דרבי וולס שאני מניינא דרבי דכולהו
ממינאי ומהצד
הוו
מתחילי. Amar Rav Papa bereih deRav Avya veisayma Rav Hillel bereih deRabbi
Valles shani minyana deRabbi dechulhu mimenai umehatzad havu maschali. In רבי's it
was different, he was such an ענו anav so modest that he
did not demand in monetary cases even though he had the prerogative
to speak first, he allowed other people to speak first, even though
that was the honor due to him. ואמר רב פפא וכיון דאדכרן
באגב דאדכרן ענותנותיה דרבי נדכור נמי גדלותיה, Veamar Rav Papa vekeivan deadkaran
beagav deadkaran anvasnuseih deRabbi nidkor nami gadluseih, since we mentioned implicitly mentioned
the humility of רבי, we're going to also mention his greatness. ואמר
רב פפא בריה דרב אויא ואי תימא רבי הילל בריה דרב וולס
Veamar Rav Papa bereih deRav Avya veisayma Rabbi Hillel bereih deRav Valles
מימות משה
ועד רבי—from Mimoyes Moshe vead Rabbi the time of משה Moshe until
רבי—לא מצינו תורה Torah וגדולה במקום אחד. We did not find great
תורה Torah greatness and also other greatness like political greatness. משה Moshe
was, you know, the political head of the people and רבי was
the political head. So the גמרא Gemara says is that really true,
that we never found them unified in one person? ולא והא הוי
יהושע? Velo veha havai Yehoshua? What about יהושע? Yehoshua? He was great
in תורה Torah. and the political leader. No, הוה אלעזר. Havai Elazar.
אלעזר Elazar was there, so even though יהושע Yehoshua had both, he
wasn't sort of the, you know, the greatest in תורה. Torah There
was somebody else there. It's not just that you didn't have them
combined but the essence is that that person was the supreme authority
in both. And אלעזר Elazar was sort of seen as a competing
figure. הוה אלעזר. Havai Elazar. So
the גמרא Gemara says
והא הוה פנחס? Veha havai Pinchas? What about פנחס? After יהושע Yehoshua
died, הוו זקנים, Havu zekenim, there were the elders, he wasn't the
only authority. והא הוה שאול? Veha havai Shaul? How about King שאול?
Shaul? הוה שמואל. Havai Shmuel. Again, not that שמואל Shmuel had political
power but religious power, meaning so he wasn't the only authority in
both or the only supreme authority in both. והנח נפשיה, Vehanach nafshieh,
but שמואל Shmuel died? No, כולהו שני קאמרינן. Kulhu shenei kaamarinan. These
figures, their entire careers they were the only authority. And in the
case of שאול, Shaul, שמואל Shmuel was a competing authority for some
of his career. והא הוה דוד? Veha havai David? How about דוד?
David? So he was again rabbinic mindset, this תורה Torah great or
whatever, and he was the king. So the גמרא Gemara says הא
הוה עירא היאירי, Ha havai Ira Hayairi, who is seen as a
competing rabbinic authority, תורה authority. והנח נפשיה, Vehanach nafshieh, but he died.
כולהו שני קאמרינן. Kulhu shenei kaamarinan. No, but And we need somebody
who the entire, their entire career, they were the only authority in,
you know, supreme authority in both of these areas. והוה שלמה *Vahavei
Shlomo*, והוה שלמה *Hava Shlomo*, king and a greatest scholar. והוה שמעי
בן גרא *Hava Shimi ben Gera* who was also a great Torah
scholar. וקטליה *Vekatlei* but Shlomo killed him. כולהו שני קיימין *Kuleihu shenei
kayamin*. Okay, it doesn't matter. We need somebody who has the, again,
the greatest authority their entire career. והוה חזקיה *Vahavei Chizkiyah*, והוה חזקיה
*Hava Chizkiyah*? והוה שבנא *Hava Shevna*. There was this Shevna who was
a great Torah authority. ואיקטיל *Veiktil*, he was killed. כולהו שני קיימין
*Kuleihu shenei kayamin*. So there was part of Chizkiyah's career where he
was the sole authority, but no, you need this person to have
been the supreme authority their entire career. והוה עזרא *Vahavei Ezra*, והוה
עזרא *Hava Ezra*? והוה נחמיה בן חכליה *Hava Nechemiah ben Chakalyah*. He
was also like a competing Torah/political authority. Okay. אמר אדא בר אהבה
*Amar Adda bar Ahava*, I'll say a similar thing. מימות רבי ועד
רב אשי *Miyemot Rebbi ve'ad Rav Ashi*, from the time of Rebbi
to Rav Ashi, לא מצינו תורה וגדולה במקום אחד Lo matzinu Torah
ugedulah bemakom echad. *lo matzinu Torah u'gedulah bemakom echad*. So presumably Rav
Ashi was a also a political leader. ולא *Velo*? והוה הונא בר
נתן *Vahavei Huna bar Natan*? Wasn't there Huna bar Natan who was
very close to the king? As Tosafot says. So the Gemara says
no. הונא בר נתן מיכף הוה כייף ליה לרב אשי *Huna bar
Natan mikaf hava kayaf leih le'Rav
Ashi*. He was not the greatest Torah authority. He was, he was,
you know, submitted to the authority of Rav Ashi. Okay. Fine. דיני
נפשות מתחילין מן הצד *Dinei nefashot matchilin min hatzad*. So
monetary cases you start from the elder. Capital cases you start from
a junior. מנא הני מילי *Mena hanei milei*? What do you know
this from? רבי אחא בר פפא *Rebbi Acha bar Papa* אמר קרא
*amar kra* says, לא תענה על ריב *Lo ta'aneh al riv*. לא
תענה על רב *Lo ta'aneh al rav*. Don't respond back when an
elder speaks. Now the question is: so therefore, since you have to
be able to have all the voices heard by capital crimes, you
have to therefore allow a junior to speak first. The question is
what about monetary crimes or monetary cases, civil disputes? Does the same
rule apply that you're not allowed to respond back, you know? If
so, then it's really a court of one. It's not a court
of three. Because there we know you afford the honor by letting
the elder speak first. So Tosafot has two answers. One is: you
respond back but you could do it as a question. Rather than
saying "I disagree," you would say "Isn't it possible that..."? Okay, but
that would still very much hamper the debate. So the other answer
Tosafot says is this prohibition of answering back is only in capital
cases, not in civil cases. Not exactly clear why, but what it
works out is that you have a mirror image. In civil cases,
you show respect by letting the elder speak first and then though
you're allowed to speak afterwards. Okay, and that's a way of showing
respect. Right, that's one explanation the Yerushalmi has. לא תענה על ריב
*Lo ta'aneh al riv* doesn't mean don't respond back. It means don't
speak up first. You let him speak first but then you're allowed
to have your opinion heard. And in capital cases, it's the reverse,
you know? You speak first, okay, and but after he speaks you're
not allowed to respond back. And you understand that because even if
you're allowed to respond back, once the elder had spoken, you would
hesitate to say your differing opinion. So in capital cases to protect
the person's innocence, we ensure that the elder speaks last and the
way we ensure, we afford the, we accord the respect is by
saying that you're not allowed to respond after he spoke. Okay. רבה
בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן מהכא *Rabbah bar bar Chana amar
Rebbi Yochanan mehacha*, from here, ויאמר דוד לאנשיו חגרו איש את חרבו
ויחגרו איש את חרבו *Vayomer David le'anashav chigru ish et charbo vayachgru
ish et charbo*. So everybody girded their sword, which is again understood
here to mean, you know, read in sort of this case about
judging and not necessarily, you know, sort of the metaphor of war.
ויחגור גם דוד את חרבו *Vayachgor gam David et charbo*. Okay, and
that was where they were judging Nabal. אמר רב *Amar Rav*, שונה
אדם לתלמידו ודן עמו בדיני נפשות *Shoneh adam letalmedo vedan imo bedinei
nefashot*. A person can teach a student and negate him in a
capital case, which the Gemara's going to understand to mean that he
can be part of the vote. And Rashi says that explicitly, which
is very bizarre because if he wasn't part of the Sanhedrin, you
can't just stam add him in. I mean there are cases where
you add pairs to the Sanhedrin, but this idea that the talmid
gets to vote is a strange idea that I don't really fully
understand. Okay, but the Gemara's question is not why does he get
to vote, but why does it count as a separate vote? The
Gemara says מיתיבי *metivei*, I'll ask you on this. הטהרות והטמאות האב
ובנו הרב ותלמידו *Hateharot vehate'me'ot ha'av uveno harav vetalmedo*, when you're dealing
with kashrut cases, like you know, halakhic issues which are not disputes,
so then a son and father and a rabbi and a student
מונין להם שנים *monin lahem shenayim*. They can count as two because
that's not a formal Beit Din. If it was a formal Beit
Din, you couldn't have a father and a son altogether. Rashi says,
you know, one rabbi could pasken these cases, so there the rules
of counting are much looser and there, if they're going to take
a vote, you know, rabbi and student, father and son can count
as separate votes. Okay, even if you'll often assume that obviously a
rabbi's going to, a student will follow his rabbi and maybe shouldn't
count, you know, allow it to count twice. But nevertheless, it counts
as a separate vote. That by cases that don't really need a
vote. אבל דיני ממונות dinei mamonos ודיני נפשות ודיני מכות קידוש החדש
ועיבור השנה *Aval dinei mamonot udinei nefashot udinei makot kiddush hachodesh ve'ibur
hashanah*, but civil cases and capital cases and lashes, sanctifying the new
moon and intercalating the year, where you do need a formal Beit
Din and a formal count, אב ובנו הרב ותלמידו אין מונין להם
אלא אחד *av uveno harav vetalmedo ein monin lahem ela echad*. Father
and son, rabbi and student you only count one because you assume
that they're just following,
unless let's say they actually voted against one another. But assuming they
voted the same way, it's not really a second vote. They're just
follow, you know, the student is just following what his רבי *rebbe*
said. Okay. Now, the problem is, what do you mean father and
son? They're not allowed to be on a בית דין beit din,
*Beis Din*. So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, well, that's why they only
count one because they're not both on the בית דין beit din,
*Beis Din*. תוספות *Tosafot* says maybe we're talking about a בית דין
beis din *Beis Din* of קידוש החודש *Kiddush HaChodesh* which could allow
for relatives. Okay, but let's bracket father and son. Anyway, here it
seems like, you know, that the student cannot be on the בית
דין *Beis Din*. So maybe it doesn't mean you שלעפ *schlep* the
student in and he wasn't on the בית דין *Beis Din*. The
point is that the student was a part of the בית דין
*Beis Din* and but and but it's not a separate vote. It's
seen as the same vote with the רבי *rebbe*. So, how's this
possible? How do you deal with this? So is it the same
vote or a different vote? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says פפא
ל"ו ע"ב
*Papa thirty-six lamed vav amud bet*, when did רב *Rav* say that
a student and a a רבי *rebbe* and a student counts as
a separate vote? That's when the student had a certain degree of
independence like רב כהנא *Rav Kahana* and רב אשי *Rav Ashi*. לגמריה
דרב הוו צריכי *ligmarei de-Rav hava tzerikhi*, okay that they would need
the, you know, they would need the teaching of their רבי *rebbe*
because, you know, in those days they didn't have written books. So
all of the information you got, you needed to get from your
רבי *rebbe*. So they needed the רבי'ס *rebbe's* information, his material, all
of the traditions that he passed down. Okay. But לסבריה דרב לא
הוו צריכי *lisvarei de-Rav lo hava tzerikhi*, but they didn't need their
רבי'ס *rebbe's* analysis. They said, you give me the information, I'll do
the analysis myself. So if you really have an independent mind, obviously
your going, your vote is going to be a distinct vote. It's
very interesting in the area of הלכה *halakha*, you know, if you're
trying to count how many פוסקים *poskim* say one way and how
many פוסקים *poskim* say another way and you have a case where
like, you know, תוספות *Tosafot* says it and, you know, the רא"ש
*Rosh* says it and the מרדכי *Mordechai* says it and the תרומת
הדשן *Terumat HaDeshen* says it, they're all really, is that multiple votes
or is that all following the same opinion? You know, so it's
an interesting type of a question here. Obviously sometimes they do have
different opinions. So, you know, even though they're often influenced by a
similar way of thinking. So here it speaks about, you know, when
somebody thinks by themselves that even if they are have a רבי-תלמיד
*rebbe-talmid* relationship, it counts as a separate vote. אמר רבי אבהו *Amar
Rabbi Abahu*, עשרה דברים יש בין דיני ממונות dinei mamonos לדיני נפשות
*asara devarim yesh bein dinei mammonos le-dinei nefashos*. In our משנה Mishna.
*Mishnah* there are ten differences. You can go and count them. Between
ממונות *mammonos* and נפשות *nefashos*. וכולן אינן נוהגין בשור הנסקל *Ve-khulan einan
nohagin beshor haniskal*. But this don't apply to a שור הנסקל *shor
haniskal*. א שור הנסקל *A shor haniskal* although gets a בית דין
*Beis Din* of 23 because we say you treat it like the
way you would execute a person, that's only just formal requirement of
23. All of the other differences are to protect the person's possible
innocence and not to take an innocent life. You know, that you
need a majority of two, how who opens up the deliberation, you
don't finish it on the same day. Those things do not apply
by a שור הנסקל *shor haniskal*. You don't try to protect the
שור הנסקל *shor haniskal*, quite the opposite maybe. You try to ensure
that this animal that could, you know, be a very dangerous animal
is put to death. So those differences do not apply. חוץ מעשרים
ושלושה *Chutz mi-esrim u-shelosha*. The only one is the בית דין *Beis
Din* of 23. מנאן הני מילי *Minan hanei milei*? Where do you
get this from? אמר רב אחא בר פפא *Amar Rav Aha bar
Papa*, דאמר קרא *de-amar kra* says, לא תטה משפט אבינך בריבו *lo
tateh mishpat evyonkha berivo*. Do not incline the judgment about the poor
person. And here that's read as: don't vote against the poor person's
life or anybody's life with just one. You need a majority of
two. So משפט אבינך אי אתה מטה *mishpat evyonkha is atah matteh*,
so that's by a poor person or what of a human, you
cannot judge against him by a majority of one. אבל אתה מטה
משפט של שור הנסקל *Aval atah matteh mishpat shel shor haniskal*. But
you can judge against a שור הנסקל *shor haniskal* by a majority
of one and all the other things that are protect a possibly
innocent life would not apply by a שור הנסקל *shor haniskal*. It
would be dealt with like a monetary case.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says עשרה *asara*, what do you
mean tens? הא תשעה הויין *Ha tish’a havyan*. There's only nine in
our משנה *Mishnah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* then like it asks
a question and it's classic like a Jew, asks a question on
the question. What do you mean there are only nine? הא עשרה
הויין *Ha asara havyan*. There are ten. ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* said there were
nine. You'd have to go count. Anyway, it says, no, משום *mishum*,
here's why we were challenging your claim of ten and we treated
as nine, משום דאין הכל כשרין לעשרים ושלושה חדא היא *mishum de-ein
hakol kesherin le-esrim u-shelosha khada hi*. The idea that not everybody can
be on a capital case, on a judge, and that you need
23 is the same basic point. 23 means it's a סנהדרין Sanhedrin.
*Sanhedrin*. Once it's a סנהדרין Sanhedrin *Sanhedrin*, implicitly the criteria of who
is a judge is different. So we were counting it as nine.
All right. So now that we're choosing to count it as nine,
we're asking you why did you say they were ten? So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, הא איכא אחריתי *ha ika achriti*. No, there's another
one that makes ten. דתניא *De-tanya*, as it's taught, אין מושיבין בסנהדרין
זקן וסריס *ein moshivin besanhedrin zaken ve-saris*. It's not only questions of
lineage who can't be on a capital case, a זקן *zaken*, an
elderly person, who, you know, might be רש"י *Rashi* says so old
that they sort of are, you know, have רש"י *Rashi* says ששכח
כבר צער גידול בנים *sheshakhakh kevar tza'ar giddul banim*, forgets the experience
of raising kids, you know, and maybe sometimes older people are a
little set in their ways. So a concern that they don't have
the right type of, you know,
emotions to necessarily be dealing, to judge these cases in a way
that will protect the innocent people. או סריס *O saris*, a eunuch,
who never had kids, ומי שאין לו בנים *u-mi she-ein lo banim*.
Or, you know, if you never had kids, you don't go through
the experience of... of the challenges of that which give you the
type of tolerance and patience and maybe compassion that you need to
be a judge.
Obviously these are pretty global statements, no, very broad generalizations, but this
is done to possibly, you know, not chew out everybody but obviously
to protect the possibly innocent victim or accused. רב יהודה מוסיף אף
אכזרית, somebody who is known to be cruel, which is the person
you would like to exclude from the very beginning, but it's harder
to quantify.
וחילופיהן במסית, v'chilufei b'meisis, the opposite would be true by somebody who
seduces people to idolatry, you would want the cruel people on this
court, you're trying to get that guy convicted. רחמנא אמר לא תחמול
ולא תכסה עליו, Rachmana amar lo sachmol v'lo sikaseh alav, don't have
compassion, don't do anything to try to be biased in his favor.
Okay. הכל כשרים לדון דיני ממונות, Hakol k'sherim ladun dinei mamonos, everybody
can judge דיני ממונות. dinei mamonos. הכל לאתויי מאי, Hakol l'asuyei mai,
what does that include? אמר רב יהודה לאתויי ממזר, Amar Rav Yehuda
l'asuyei mamzer, a ממזר, mamzer, because the משנה, you know, who's excluded
from דיני נפשות is anybody who can't marry a כהן, Kohen, like
you know, a question like of a חלל or whatever, but who's
good for דיני ממונות is even more than that, is even like
a ממזר mamzer who can't marry another Jew, even that person is
good for דיני ממונות. הא תנינא
חדא זימנא, Ha tanyina chada zina, one minute, we taught this already.
כל הראוי לדון דיני נפשות ראוי לדון דיני ממונות ויש ראוי לדון
דיני ממונות ואינו ראוי לדון דיני נפשות, Kol hara'uy ladun dinei nefashos
ra'uy ladun dinei mamonos v'yesh hara'uy ladun dinei mamonos v'ein ra'uy ladun
dinei nefashos, if you can be on a
capital case you can be on a civil, and there's good for
civil and not for capital, who is that? ואבינא בה לאתויי מאי,
v'avina bah l'asuyei mai, who does that include? ואמר רב יהודה לאתויי
ממזר, v'amar Rav Yehuda l'asuyei mamzer, to include a ממזר. mamzer. So
the גמרא asks, so you see we've already taught a ממזר. mamzer.
חדא לאתויי גר, chada l'asuyei ger, find, one of these משניות Mishnayos
teaches a גר, ger, who also lineage is a little bit not
standard, וחדא לאתויי ממזר, v'chada l'asuyei mamzer, a ממזר. mamzer. וצריכא, v'tzricha,
and you need to say both.
דאי אשמעינן גר, de-i ashmeinan ger, if you said a גר ger
can be on a דיני ממונות case, fine, because he could marry
a Jew, אבל ממזר אימא לא, aval mamzer eima lo, a ממזר
mamzer can't marry a Jew, maybe you see him more as outside
and can't even be on a דיני ממונות case.
ואי אשמעינן ממזר, v'i ashmeinan mamzer, דבא מטיפה כשירה, d'ba mi-tipa ksheira,
he comes from Jewish
parents, אבל גר דלא בא מטיפה כשירה, aval ger d'lo ba mi-tipa
ksheira, a גר ger who doesn't come from Jewish parents, maybe you
would think that therefore that should be a basis of exclusion, אימא
לא, eima lo, צריכא, tzricha, so it has to tell you both
can be on דיני ממונות. Now there's an interesting issue because another
גמרא says a גר ger can be on a case where he's
judging his fellow גר. ger. So the question is do you read
those as you need both or either? רש"י says either, a גר
ger can be on any case of monetary issues or even on
a capital case if you're judging a fellow גר. ger. תוספות says
you need both, which is very, very restrictive. A גר ger can
only be on a monetary case and only one that is judging
also another גר, ger, which is not what this גמרא sounds like
at all. Okay. ואינו כל כשר לדון דיני נפשות, v'eino kol kasher
ladun dinei nefashos, and not everybody can do capital cases. מאי טעמא,
mai ta'ama, what's the reason? דתני רב יוסף, d'tani Rav Yosef, כשם
שבית דין מנוקים בצדק, k'shem she-beit din menukim b'tzedek, the same way
they have to be like pure in righteousness, כך מנוקים מכל מום,
kach menukim mi-kol mum, so they have to be free from a
blemish and here blemish meaning lineage type of a blemish. אמר אמימר
מאי קרא, Amar Ameimar mai kra, where do you know this from?
כולך יפה רעייתי ומום אין בך, Kulach yafa ra'ayasi u-mum ein bach,
we'll see this using שיר השירים Shir HaShirim to describe a בית
דין, you're beautiful, there's no blemish, and understood to be a blemish
of lineage. So the גמרא says ודילמא מום ממש, v'dilma mum mamash,
maybe it means a physical blemish. אמר רב אחא בר יעקב אמר
קרא, Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar kra, the verse says והתיצבו
שם עמך, v'hityatzvu sham imach, by משה Moshe and the seventy elders.
עמך בדומין לך, imach b'domin lach, like you. Now how does that,
we know that that means, you know, lineage rather than a physical
blemish? But we don't. But somehow presumably, you know, if we didn't
have the emphasis of מום, mum, we wouldn't have started even thinking
about physical blemish. So the idea is that we'll assume the greater
sense of identification is around this issue of lineage, as physical should
not be a basis for exclusion.
So now the גמרא says
ודילמא התם משום שכינה, v'dilma hasam mishum Shechina, maybe there the need
to be like משה Moshe for whatever, however you define מום, mum,
is because of the divine presence which was resting on the seventy
elders. Maybe it's not true about every בית דין, every סנהדרין. אלא
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר קרא, Ela amar Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak amar kra, the verse says ונשאו אתך, v'nasu itach, אתך בדומין
לך להוו. itach b'domin lach l'havei. So when יתרו Yisro says to
משה Moshe they'll carry the burden with you, so that's not about
God's presence resting on them and there too you have to be
like משה, Moshe, which is understood to mean free from at least
this issue of a lineage problem or difference. Okay, let's just read
the next משנה. סנהדרין היתה כחצי עגולה גורן עגולה, Sanhedrin haysa k'chatzi
agula goren agula, it was like half of a threshing floor עגולה,
agula, it was a circle, it was a half circle, okay, and
that's way the judges could all see one another, everybody would have
an equal voice, presumably in their deliberations, they could also all have
equal viewing of the witnesses and of the litigants, so it created
obviously a greater, like lesser of a hierarchy but also greater sense
that everybody could immediately sort of have an equal view and equal
directness. כדי שיהיו רואים זה את זה, k'dei she-yiyu ro'im zeh es
zeh, in order that they should be able to see one another
for the various reasons that I just said.
ושני סופרי הדיינים עומדים לפניהם, u-shnei sofrei hadayanim omdim lifneihem, and the
two scribes were standing in their presence. אחד מימין ואחד משמאל, echad
mi-yamin v'echad mi-smol, one on the right and one on the left
at the edges of the circles, of the half circles, וכותבין דברי
המזכים ודברי המחייבים, v'kosvin divrei hamzakim v'divrei hamchayavim, they would write whatever
everybody said, all the arguments. for innocence or the arguments for guilt.
And they would write duplicate records so you could check them against
one another. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer now Rabbi Yehuda said
שלושה shlosha there would be three because to write everything would be
a little burdensome so you would split up the work. אחד כותב
דברי מזקין echad kotev divrei mazakin one would write only the arguments
in favor. אחד כותב דברי מחייבין echad kotev divrei mechayvin the others
would write the arguments for guilt. והשלישי כותב דברי מזקין ודברי מחייבין
ve-hashlishi kotev divrei mazakin ve-divrei mechayvin the third one had the hardest
job he would have to write everything and therefore at least according
that would be the way to double check if there was any
doubt or question about what was actually said but you split up
the basic job so to make sure everything gets recorded. בשלוש שורות
של תלמידי חכמים יושבים לפניהם be-shalosh shurot shel talmidei chachamim yoshvim lifneihem
and that half circle, there would be three other half circles that
would be sort of like you know they'd all be like these
parallel half circles, one inside of the other, and these would be
three rows of students.
כל אחד ואחד מכיר את מקומו kol echad ve-echad makir et mekomo
everybody knew where they sat because there was a hierarchy although it
was a half circle, you weren't, you know, which way you were
on the inner half circle or the outer one, where were you
in that circle, at which edge were you, and there was a
clear hierarchy. Okay. By the way, רש״י Rashi says there were three
because he said you might have to by 23 start adding people
till you could get to 71. That would require 48 people more
from 23 to 71. 48 would be two rows of 24. But
you can't have a row that's bigger than the judges, your circle
can't be bigger than the circle's judges, so it would be two
rows of 23 and then two. What are you going to do
with just two people that's not fit that circle is so small
so that required a third circle of 23. Okay now.
הוצרכו לסמוך hutzrechu lismoch let's say one of the judges died or
had to recuse himself or said איני יודע eini yode-a and you
had to go ahead and give סמיכה semicha and here it's very
clear that if to put somebody on the סנהדרין required giving them
סמיכה semicha right because we've implicitly been talking about this but it's
very funny how sort of subtle it is. To deal with a
capital case you need the סמיכה semicha that goes back to משה
רבנו Moshe Rabbeinu you have to be the אלהים, elohim, you know,
you have to sort of be representing God's authority, you need that
formal סמיכה. semicha. So if we now needed to put somebody on
our בית דין that one of the judges had to leave or
whatever and we now need to put one or two people up
we're going to have to give them סמיכה. semicha.
Okay, סומכין מן הראשונה somchin min harishona so you give the סמיכה
semicha to the person who is top of the line, you know,
again there are these half circles but there's the inner circle and
the person who's at the head of you know who's in the
front what's defined as the front part of that half circle not
the back part or the middle. So סומכין מן הראשונה. somchin min
harishona.
אחד מן השנייה בא לו לראשונה echad min hashniya ba lo larishona
so then everybody shifts one. It's almost like a pecking order with
all the half circles, it's very interesting right the sort of egalitarian
aspect and the pecking and the hierarchy. So then everybody, you know,
number two moves to number one, number three moves to number two,
number four moves to number three, everybody moves up. So then one
seat is vacant in inner row number one, so the last, the
top guy on inner row number two moves to the last seat
of inner row number one. אחד מן השנייה בא לו לראשונה echad
min hashniya ba lo larishona ואחד מן השלישית ve-echad min hashlishit and
then everybody in row two moves up and the last seat in
two is left vacant, so the head guy in number three בא
לו לשנייה ba lo lashniya sits in the back seat of number
two and then a seat at the end of row three is
opened up. בוררים להם עוד אחד מן הקהל borim lahem od echad
min hakahal so you find somebody now from the larger community, you
find somebody now from the larger community who's now worthy of being
in this row of students.
Okay, אחד מן הקהל echad min hakahal ומושיבין אותו בשלישית u-moshivin oto
bashlishit and you have him sit at the end of the third
row. ולא היה יושב במקומו של ראשון. ve-lo haya yoshev bimkomo shel
rishon. Don't just say why do we have to shift everybody, just
find somebody and have him go to the empty seat. Of course
that would be ironic right, some random person now gets to jump
to the head of the line or even to the head of
the third row. You wouldn't do that. אלא
יושב במקום הראוי לו. ela yoshev bamakom harauy lo. Everybody sits in
the appropriate seat. So with egalitarianism there's also this hierarchy and this
order.